大家好 我是《每日宇航员》的Tim Dodd
- Hi, it's me Tim Dodd, The Everyday Astronaut.
SpaceX以下简称太空叉
我身后是SpaceX的Starship的原型机
Behind me is SpaceX's Starship prototype,
它缺了点东西
and it's missing something.
好吧其实缺的东西不少
Well actually it's missing a lot of stuff right now.
其中一样缺少的零件
But one thing that's missing
在以后也不打算安装上去
that there's no plans to put on it
那就是发射逃逸系统
is a launch escape system,
或者逃逸塔之类的东西
or a launch abort tower of any kind.
这款火箭将不使用任何发射逃逸机构
No mechanical aborts are gonna be on this rocket at all.
这是个好主意吗
Is that a good idea?
事后诸葛亮地讲
Hindsight is always 20/20,
航天飞机饱受争议的点
and one of the biggest criticisms of the Space Shuttle,
就是它号称可复用
which also claim to be reusable,
而且像普通飞机一样可靠
and airliner like reliable,
且航天飞机也没有任何发射逃逸系统
was it didn't have any kind of launch abort system.
和太空叉宣传自家Starship的内容一样
And that's the same type of thing SpaceX is claiming the Starship.
为何历史总是惊人的相似？
So why are we doomed to see history repeat itself?
而众所周知 太空叉的载人龙飞船和波音的星际线
And as we know, spaceX's Dragon Capsule and Boeing Starliner
在发射逃逸系统上都有些许问题
both have had problems with their launch escape systems.
那么今天我们将来讨论 这些额外的装置是必需的吗？
So today we are going to debate is all that extra stuff necessary?
逃逸系统会让火箭更加安全吗？
Does it actually make for a safer vehicle?
希望大家看完本期视频后
And hopefully by the end of this video
我们能明白把人放在没有任何逃逸系统的火箭上是不是个好主意
we'll know whether or not it's a good idea
to put people on top of this rocket without any kind of mechanical abort system.
走起！
Let's get started.
这又是一个无数人问过我的很好的话题
This is another one of those topics I've been asked about over and over and for good reasons!
尤其是最近我们看到了商业载人航天项目
Especially now that we're seeing the commercial crew program
也把发射逃逸系统放入日程
put launch abort systems through their paces.
与之关联更大的事情是
And this has come up even more relevant ever since
我们在Boca Chica见证了Starship原型机MK-1
we've witnessed the failure of the MK-1 Starship prototype down in Boca Chica
发射台上压力测试时炸飞了顶盖
while it pressure testing on the launch pad.
如果上面有人会怎样？
What if there were people onboard?
为啥太空叉不考虑在上面安装发射中止系统？
Why isn't SpaceX thinking about putting a launch abort system on it?
有的粉丝们可能已经看过我之前一期视频
As you may know, I've already talked a good amount about abort systems in a video
av82858385
介绍了为何太空叉的载人龙飞船和波音的星际线飞船都选择了
explaining why both SpaceX's Crew Dragon capsule and Boeing's Starliner have opted
液体火箭发动机推式逃逸系统
for liquid fueled pusher abort systems,
而没有选择传统的固体火箭发动机推式逃逸系统
as opposed to a more traditional puller system with solid rocket motors.
如果大家想复习一下逃逸系统
So if you need an overview on those systems,
请先去看看那个视频！
definitely check that video out!
应该会让大家对现代逃逸系统有一些额外的看法
It should help give you some extra perspective on modern abort systems.
对于误入本视频的观众
Now in case you didn't notice when you clicked on this video,
请先看一下进度条长度
this is a again another pretty long one.
我又不喜欢蜻蜓点水浮光略影
As you may know, I don't like to skim the surface of topics,
我寻找答案过程中喜欢一路深挖下去  顺便讲讲历史说说数据
I like to actually dive in deep and get into the data and history in order to find the answers.
本期视频将涉及大量细节 图表 数据
So we're going to get into a lot of little details, charts and data and more charts and more data.
我们将了解火箭的认证
We'll go over certifications of rockets,
火箭发动机的可靠性
the reliability of rocket engines,
Starship设计的风险与好处
the risks and benefits of Starship's designs,
并纵观整个人类航天史 让大家了解到
and even look at the whole history of human spaceflight and figure out
逃逸系统到底拯救了几条飞船上的人命
how many times an abort system has actually saved the lives of those on board.
视频结尾 也不会是我对于Starships没装逃逸塔是好是坏的单纯的观点
By the end of this video it won't just be my opinion
on whether Starship without an abort system is a good idea or not,
而是一个分析性的总结
it'll mostly be an analytical based summary.
为了各位的观看体验
So to make it easy for your viewing pleasure,
逃逸系统工作原理 03:05
航天飞机安全裕度 05:25
航天飞机危险因素 10:40
Starship与航天飞机之不同 16:00
发动机的可靠性 21:00
Starship逃逸系统可选方案 30:35
逃逸系统是否真的会让火箭更安全 34:30
如何提升无逃逸系统火箭的安全性 38:55
逃逸系统对载人航天的必要性 41:50
我将列出本视频各个部分的空降坐标
here are the timestamps of each topic we're going to talk about
欢迎各位跳转空降
in case you want to go back and review something.
视频详情也会列出空降坐标与本视频的文字版
There's also links in the description below to those timestamps and an article version of this video
方便各位回溯其中引用的数据
as well for you to easily go back over some numbers and sources.
逃逸系统工作原理
好 先讲逃逸系统
Okay, so abort systems.
其实原理很简单
The idea is pretty simple.
火箭是很复杂的
Rockets are fickle beasts.
它们脚踩世界上最精密的工程产物
They're riding the finest engineering line possible.
肩扛极大的载荷负担与恶劣环境 温度
They need to handle extremely intense loads, temperatures and environments
还要保证自身越轻越好
while also being as lightweight as possible.
上百万个零件能协同工作 不出问题简直是奇迹
Since there's literally millions of moving parts, it's honestly a miracle they work at all.
当你把一个大活人放在由上百万个零件组装起来的
So when you're putting someone on top of a vehicle it's basically a giant bomb with a nozzle
能正常运转的巨型窜天猴顶端时
that has to have millions of parts work properly in order to not fail,
在发生意外时有一个备份方案总是件好事
it's generally considered a good idea to have a back up if things don't go as planned.
纵观人类航天史
Throughout most history of human spaceflight,
有一种方案几乎统治了所有发射逃逸系统
there's been one method that has dominated launch abort systems,
那就是固体火箭逃逸塔
and that's a solid rocket motor launch escape tower.
这种塔型结构放置在乘员舱的顶部
This is the tower that sits on top of the crew module
大家可能在水星号 联盟号 阿波罗 乃至NASA的猎户座飞船上都看过
that you may have noticed on vehicles like Mercury, Soyuz, Apollo and even NASA's Orion capsule.
个别的飞船比如东方号 双子号和早期的航天飞机
A few vehicles like Vostok, Gemini and early Space Shuttle's
使用弹射座椅作为其逃逸系统
had ejection seats as an escape system,
我有一期视频详细介绍了这个内容
and I've got a video about that if you want to hear more about it,
但甭管是弹射座椅
but regardless of whether it's an ejection seat,
还是逃逸塔 还是现代的液体火箭推式逃逸系统
a launch tower, or a more modern liquid pusher system,
概念都是一样的
the concept is the same.
如果逃逸系统检测到推力减少
If the escape system detects either a loss of thrust,
飞行路径严重偏离
a severe deviation in flight path,
甚至检测到燃料箱的破裂
or even detects a rupture in the tanks,
都会触发逃逸系统工作
it'll triggers the abort system.
早期的火箭 可能还有一些现代火箭
Early rockets, and probably some modern ones,
这点我不是太确定
I couldn't actually find the answer to that,
有三条传感器连出的线缆沿着燃料罐走行
have a trio of sensor wires running the length of the fuselage.
一旦任意两条失去联系
If any two of those wires lose contact,
就表明燃料罐出现了破损
this indicates the fuselage had broken up,
就会触发逃逸系统
which then would trigger the abort system.
发射逃逸系统也可以由宇航员进行手动触发
The launch abort system can also be manually triggered by an astronaut
比如发现了系统没有检测到的致命故障
who may notice a critical flaw that the system doesn't detect.
当逃逸系统被触发时
Once an abort system is triggered,
逃逸发动机启动 分级系统让逃逸系统把飞船带离火箭
the stage separation system needs to let go of the spacecraft as the abort motors are fired,
so it can pull it clean from the rocket.
逃逸发动机启动后 给乘员舱的加速度相当大
When the motors actually fire it accelerates the crew capsule away extremely quickly.
真的相当大的G值 至少10G
I mean abort motors can pull some serious Gs, like over 10 Gs.
发射逃逸系统是公认的保证乘员安全最好的系统
So launch abort systems were pretty much considered the best way to keep a crew safe.
但如果你把整个火箭系统造得更加安全呢？
But what if you just made your entire system more safe?
如果你有足够的冗余系统
What if you made more redundant systems
over-engineer "过设计" 也叫"过度设计"
每个零件都为了更高的安全裕度而"过设计"呢？
and over-engineered every single part to even greater safety margins?
设计一款像民航客机一样安全可靠的火箭
Designing a rocket to be as reliable as an airliner
正是NASA当年设计航天飞机时候的初衷
that's exactly what NASA was hoping to do when engineering the Space Shuttle.
这款飞船名叫航天飞机
The vehicle was called a space shuttle,
一款能够往返近地轨道一百次 像民航客机一样的飞船
an airliner like spacecraft capable of over 100 trips from Earth into Earth orbit.
他们认为 如果航天飞机的每个零件都进行过设计
The thought being if every single part of the Space Shuttle was over engineered,
那么飞船和乘员的损失就会降低
the chance of loss of vehicle and crew would be very low.
低到可能会比额外加装运动部件与系统从而构建有效的逃逸系统还要更安全
So low it might actually be safer than adding additional moving parts
and systems necessary to make an effective abort system.
在阿波罗那个NASA好像钱多得没处花的时代
During the Apollo era when NASA had what now seems like unlimited funding,
他们找到了通用电气做了一个全数值概率——我没念错吧
they contracted General Electric to do a full numerical probabilistic, how do you say that word?
哥爱 概 勒玉 率 应该没念错
"Probabilistic"? sure
人类能够安全登月并返回地球的全数值概率风险评估
risk assessment of landing a human on the Moon and returning them safely to Earth.
通用电气得到的数字是5——百分之五
The number GE came up with was five, 5%.
人类成功登月并安全返回的成功率只有5%
A 5% chance of successfully landing a human on the Moon and bringing them home.
NASA的局长詹姆斯·韦伯肯定不乐意
NASA administrator James Webb didn't like those numbers,
而他并没有去修改火箭或任务本身
and instead of making changes to the rocket and the mission,
而是决定改变他们处理风险的工程设计方式
decided to change the way they engineered around risk.
我要指出的是这不一定是坏事
Which let me point out, isn't necessarily a bad thing.
他们研发了"故障模式"和"影响分析"
They developed something called Failure Modes and Effects Analysis
可以识别可能会导致灾难性情况的设计和硬件
which was a way to identify designs and hardware that would worse case scenario lead to catastrophe.
关键一级 如果零件失效 会导致乘员死亡或飞船损毁
关键二级 如果零件失效 会导致任务失败
关键三级 其他
关键一级R 如果两套冗余组件全部失效 会导致成员死亡或飞船损毁
关键二级R 如果两套冗余组件全部失效 会导致任务失败
它们被分类成关键一级
These were ranked as Criticality one,
可能威胁乘员生命与飞船运行
which would threaten the life of the crew or the existence of the vehicle.
关键二级 可能威胁到任务的成功 和关键三级 可能威胁其他事情
Criticality two which would threaten the mission or Criticality three for anything else.
还在零件和设计分析中为冗余系统添加了标注后缀R的级别
They also added an R as notation for redundant systems in these parts and design analysis.
在人类成功登月后 NASA的预算开始减少
With NASA's budget beginning to dwindle once humans landed on the Moon,
以及国会对即将到来的航天飞机计划支持率的降低
and congressional support for the upcoming Shuttle Program waning,
NASA不得不把航天飞机的卖点定为一款廉价可靠的主力飞船
NASA had to sell the Space Shuttle as a cheap and reliable workhorse.
甚至还要计算确切风险值
And its exact risk even had to be calculated
才能发射像伽利略号木星探测器这种钚燃料的探测器
in order to launch plutonium-fueled spacecraft like the Jupiter Probe, Galileo.
测试复杂系统的可靠性 内容包括将系统作为整体进行研究
Testing the reliability of a complex system involves studying the system as a whole,
找出潜在的故障点
identifying potential fault points,
然后收集不同环境条件下这些故障点的极限在哪
and then gathering the limits on these potential fault points over different environmental conditionals.
现在还可以使用统计模型和计算机模拟进行测试
You also test them in statistical models and computer simulations these days,
并对其进行迭代以确保计算机模拟满足真实世界的性能需求
and iterating them to make sure that the computer simulations meet the real world performance
从而确定成功率是否满足阈值需要
in order to help determine if the probability of success is above the threshold required.
每个零件都有设计规范
Each and every single part will have a design specification
和一定的安全系数 以界定它需要承受超出设计规范多大范围
and a certain safety factor for how much more it can handle beyond its design specification.
火箭上绝大多数零件的安全系数是1.5
The general rule of thumb for most parts on a rocket is a factor of safety of 1.5.
这意味着如果某个零件需要承受10牛顿的力
All this really means is if a part needs to handle 10 newtons of force,
那在测试时 它需要承受15牛顿的力且不会失效
when testing it it should be able to handle 15 newtons of force without failing.
但当零件没有良好测试或以往数据经验的话
But when there isn't good test or heritage data for a certain part,
通常会将安全系数提高到2.0
a factor of safety of 2.0 is considered a good rule of thumb.
也就是要承受两倍于需求的力
In other words engineered to handle twice that what's necessary.
但在航天飞机计划开始的时候
But by the start of the Space Shuttle program,
灾难性故障发生概率的估计范围在小于1%到小于0.001%
estimates of catastrophic failures ranged from less than 1% to less than 0.001%.
所以实际上安全性的估计范围差了几个数量级
So actually a couple orders of magnitude in its estimated range of predicted safety.
虽然当时NASA迷之乐观
Despite the optimistic nature of NASA,
他们还是给航天飞机前四发装了弹射座椅
the first four flights of the Space Shuttle had ejection seats active,
不过之后就取消了 因为使用案例非常有限
but were later ditched due to their very limited use cases
而且实际上 只有上层的乘员可以弹射出去
and the fact that they could only eject crew from the upper deck
其余中层的乘员只能等死
since the rest of the crew was on the mid deck which was below them.
但在挑战者号空难后
But after the Challenger disaster,
NASA的确考虑过使用弹射舱
NASA actually did consider utilizing an ejection cabin
可以让全体成员从航天飞机弹射出去
that could eject the entire crew module free from the Shuttle
有点像F-111s和早期B-1原型机那样
kind of like the F-111s and early B-1 prototypes,
但它太复杂 太重了
but it was deemed too complex, too heavy,
需要大量改装才能让它派上用场
and required way too many modifications to really make it feasible.
事后看来 我们知道航天飞机135次飞行有两次失败
So in hindsight, we know the shuttle wound up with two failures out of 135 flights,
一次在发射中 一次在再入大气中
one during launch and one during reentry,
成功率只有98.5%
giving it a success rate of only 98.5%,
和最初估计的安全性中最保守的估计值都差得老远
which is way off from even the most conservative estimates of safety.
也可能是因为航天飞机的教训
Likely due to the Space Shuttle's track record,
NASA改变了他们商业载人航天计划的认证系统
NASA changed their certification system for the Commercial Crew Program,
需要在上升时乘员损失率为1:500
which is required to have a probability of loss of crew at 1:500 on ascent,
返回时为1:500
1:500 on descent,
在轨时故障率为1:270
with a 1:270 chance of an issue while in orbit.
要真正实际去验证一个系统
To actually certify and validate systems,
有时就是把系统整体放到极端环境下进行测试
sometimes it comes down to just putting it all through the ringer to test the system as a whole
而不是单独测试每个部件
alongside testing each individual part.
整体测试一个系统的过程称为全面测试
Testing the system as a whole is called all-up testing,
这是NASA在阿波罗时代搞出来的东西
that's what NASA coined it during the Apollo Era,
从长远来看 相比于进行更多地面测试 分析 和使用以往数据进行认证
In the long run all-up testing might actually be a quicker route to verify the system
全面测试可能是验证系统更快的方法
versus acquiring certification through more ground tests, analysis and using heritage data
如果不进行整体全面测试 每个零件可能需要更高的安全系数
that might require a higher factor of safety per part if it's not going to be tested as a whole.
可以发现如今两家商业公司在认证方法上就有这样的不同
You can see this difference in methods play out today
太空叉选择在飞行中测试 认证他们的逃逸系统
in how SpaceX chose to validate and certify their abort system by opting to test it in flight
而波音选择通过对各个零件进行更严格的认证来验证其逃逸系统
while Boeing has opted to certify their abort system through a more stringent certification of individual parts.
既然航天飞机和Starship都没有逃逸系统
Since the Space Shuttle and Starship both lack abort systems,
那么航天飞机有哪些非常危险的设计考虑因素？
what design considerations did the Space Shuttle have that were so dangerous?
Starship又有同样的缺陷吗？
And does Starship share any of the same flaws?
航天飞机危险因素
造成航天飞机有点危险的因素有几个
There's a few things that made the Space Shuttle inherently kinda dangerous,
我们先从固体火箭助推器开始
but let's start off with those solid rocket boosters.
安装在外挂燃料箱两侧的巨大白色固体火箭助推器
Those giant white solid rocket boosters on the side of the external fuel tank
起飞时提供了超过60%的推力
actually provided over 60% of thrust at liftoff.
而且它们一旦被点燃就不能关闭
Here's the thing, once they ignited, there was no shutting them down,
你总得飞到哪去 还得赶快
you're going somewhere and you're going somewhere in a hurry.
而且希望飞的时候是头朝上尾焰朝下
Hopefully the pointy end is up and the flame-y end is down.
这意味着 无论多么严重的故障 任何逃逸系统
This meant any abort mode or abort procedure, no matter how bad or dire,
都得让火箭忍到固推烧完
required the crew ride out the boosters, seriously.
所以升空后127秒内
So for an entire 127 seconds,
一旦出现任何问题
if there was a problem,
上面的人都得默念老天保佑一定要坚持住
you just had to cross your fingers and toes that it wasn't too serious and you could keep going
主要是因为如果在这期间逃逸
This is mostly because if you were to abort
无论是让轨道器和外挂燃料箱分离 还是直接跳机
by either detaching the orbiter from the external fuel tank or by trying to jump out,
你都会被固推的尾焰吞没
you'd end up within the plume of those SRBs,
生还几率渺茫
which would be very, very lethal.
但不幸的是 有些故障 火箭真的忍不到固推烧完的时候
Unfortunately, some problems you can't just ride out,
就像1986年1月28日 挑战者号的第十次太空飞行
like on January 28th, 1986 when the Space Shuttle Challenger took to the sky on its 10th mission.
大家可能早就知道了 固定固推某段的O型圈发生泄漏
As you probably know a leaky O-ring that sealed one of the sections of the Solid Rocket Boosters sprung a leak
导致之后固推和外挂燃料箱的连接处断开
which ended up causing separation of the joint that held the SRB to the external fuel tank,
最终导致火箭彻底解体 七人全部遇难的悲剧
which then led to complete structural failure of the vehicle and tragic loss of the crew of seven.
但挑战者号空难的最大问题并不是它硬件的缺陷
But perhaps the biggest problem with the Challenger disaster wasn't a hardware problem,
而是飞行计划管理上的漏洞
but a problem with program management
与当时急于发射所带来的压力
and pressure to get that particular flight off the ground.
他们早就知道发射条件处于固推所允许的包线之外
It was known that they would be launching outside of the predetermined operating envelope of the SRBs
并且建议取消当天的发射
and it was recommended to not launch that day.
尽管使用液体燃料助推器也不会消除所有隐患
Although utilizing liquid fueled rocket boosters they probably wouldn't eliminate all potential failures,
而且可能还不如固推可靠
and it could arguably be less reliable than a solid rocket booster,
但液体火箭助推器至少能做到随时关机
but liquid rocket boosters can at least be shut down
可以提供更多的逃逸选项
which in general can open up more abort options.
来看看这个表格
Take a look at this chart.
观察黑条区域
Notice the black sections.
这些是发射中如果损失二或三台发动机会导致完全失控或结构完全损毁的区域
Yeah, those are sections of ascent where there would be a full loss of control and/or structural failure
if the vehicle were to lose two or three main engines.
所以如果你挂了两台或者三台发动机 你就完蛋了
So basically lose two of the three main engines and you're screwed.
这还没算进固推和其他别的东西的故障
And you're not even talking about having any problem with the SRBs or anything else.
但在挑战者号空难后 NASA的确增加了很多应急措施
But after Challenger disaster NASA did come up with a lot more contingencies
比如备份跑道 和标志性的橙色先进乘员逃生服
including alternate runways and the iconic orange Advanced Crew Escape Suits
呃……发生意外时 逃生用的
to you know, escape if things went wrong.
字面意思的 逃生
Literally escape,
这是新版的逃逸流程 注意到当中灰色的区域
Here's the new abort profiles see these gray sections during ascent?
这些区域意思就是让乘员跳飞机
Now the plan was for the crew to literally jump out during those sections.
大致就是小心地和外挂燃料箱分离
As in, carefully ditch the external fuel tank,
让轨道器进入稳定滑翔状态
get the orbiter into a stable glide,
解 开 安 全 带
literally unbuckle,
炸开舱门
blow the hatch,
伸出一根杆 保证你跳出去的时候不会撞上机翼
extend a freaking pole that made it so you wouldn't hit the wing when you jump out,
然后跳吧 没开玩笑
and then jump out, seriously.
说到撞上机翼 就要说到航天飞机另一大缺陷了
Speaking of hitting the wing, that's another major flaw of the Space Shuttle.
轨道器是挂在运载火箭侧面的
The orbiter was hanging off the side of the vehicle,
导致乘员舱和脆弱的隔热层直接暴露在碎冰 泡沫的冲击范围内
which put the crew module and fragile thermal protection system directly in the path of ice and foam strikes.
橙罐里装有低温的液氢液氧 外有大量绝热层
The orange external fuel tank housed cryogenic hydrogen and oxygen which had a good amount of insulation
从而给燃料保温
in order to keep them at operating temperatures.
你几乎能在所有液体火箭发射的时候看到碎冰噼里啪啦往下掉
You can actually see sheets of ice fall off basically any liquid fueled rocket at lift off,
这是个已知变量
it's a known variable,
甚至能看到大块泡沫从航天飞机外挂燃料箱上掉落
and even large chunks of foam were observed falling off the Space Shuttle's external fuel tank
但NASA后来慢慢接受了这个事实
but NASA grew more and more accepting of this fact.
当你将大块绝热泡沫
When you combine a large chunk of foam
和航天飞机脆弱的热防护系统两个因素结合到一起
and the fragile nature of the thermal protection system on the Space Shuttle,
你就会得到一个潜在的事故征候
you wind up with a real potential for disaster.
这也正是哥伦比亚号空难的罪魁祸首
And this is exactly what caused the Columbia failure.
在起飞过程中 一大块绝热泡沫击中了哥伦比亚号的机翼前缘
A large chunk of foam struck the leading edge of Columbia's wing on ascent,
在左翼的增强碳纤维热防护区上打出一个大洞
punching a large hole in the reinforced carbon-carbon section of thermal protection on the left wing.
七名乘员坐着航天飞机 带着那个会在返回时置他们于死地的大洞
The shuttle and the seven crew onboard continued to carry out their mission for 15 days
继续完成了为期15天的任务
with a hole that would doom them on reentry.
2003年2月1日 在哥伦比亚号再入地球大气时
On February 1st, 2003, as Columbia reentered the Earth's atmosphere,
机翼上的大洞让高温气流摧毁了机翼 并导致轨道器解体
the large hole in the wing caused hot plasma to essentially destroy the wing and therefore the orbiter,
七名乘员全部遇难
tragically ending the seven crew's lives who were onboard.
除了轨道器被挂在火箭侧面会遭受掉落碎片的袭击外
Besides the orbiter being slung off the side of the rocket and in harm's way of falling debris,
航天飞机的热防护层本来就很脆弱 又进一步加剧了危险性
the danger was amplified by how fragile the Space Shuttle's thermal protection system was.
航天飞机的两万四千多块硅隔热片是一块块粘在轨道器铝制机身外壳上的
The Space Shuttle's 24,000 plus silica tiles were literally glued onto the aluminum airframe of the orbiter
覆盖整个机身底部
which covered the entire bottom portion of the vehicle.
脆弱的机身不但让人头疼 还会上演各种惊魂一幕
Their fragile nature caused not only many headaches, but also led to some close calls.
最著名的就是STS-27任务中 飞行到第85秒遭受的碎片撞击
Perhaps the most well noted was STS-27 which experienced a debris strike 85 seconds into the flight.
撞击导致一块绝热瓦彻底脱落 连带伤及其他七百多块绝热瓦
This knocked a tile clean off and damaged OVER 700 other tiles!
额滴神啊
Whoa!
更加幸运的是
In the absolute luckiest of circumstances,
脱落的瓦片下方刚好是L波段天线的钢制安装板
the tile that went missing was right on top of a steel mounting plate for the L-band antenna,
钢的熔点又稍微比铝制机身高
which steel has a higher melting point than the aluminum airframe
最后轨道器极其幸运地活过了再入阶段
and by sheer luck the orbiter survived reentry
没有酿成十五年后哥伦比亚号的灾难
and didn't end up a disaster like Columbia would some 15 years later.
Starship与航天飞机之不同
现在我们知道了航天飞机的一些主要设计缺陷
So now that we know some of the major design flaws that plagued the Space Shuttle,
我们来看看Starship在设计上的不同之处
let's go over Starship and see how its design differs.
一眼就能看出 Starship是放在超重型助推顶端
Well right off the bat, Starship is on top of the Super Heavy booster,
而不是挂在侧面的
and not slung off the side.
这对于乘员舱来说显然是更加安全的位置
As we've noted, this is clearly a safer place for the crew cabin to be,
避免了很多潜在的碎片撞击风险
putting it ahead of any potential debris strikes.
但我们还是要记住一点
But we should note something that will definitely need to be studied.
Starship两侧也有机翼 在再入大气时起着关键作用
Remember, Starship also has those large flaps that are vital to its reentry.
这意味着 Starship上面级液氧和甲烷燃料罐外的冰块
This does mean there'd be potential for ice from the liquid oxygen and liquid methane tanks
仍然有风险会砸中Starship机翼前缘
on the Starship upper stage to strike the leading edge of the flaps.
这时 不锈钢机身和热防护板栓接的特性
Here's where a stainless steel body and the fact that the thermal protection plates will be bolted on
相比于脆弱的绝热瓦和增强碳纤维覆盖的铝制机身 就有着极大的优势
has a huge advantage over the fragile silica tiles and reinforced carbon-carbon covering an aluminum airframe.
所以大家别忘了 Starship的机翼前缘和下表面会作为热防护罩
So let's not forget, the leading edge and underside of the flaps of Starship will still utilize a heat shield,
但又与航天飞机的绝热瓦不同
but unlike the silica tiles of the Space Shuttle,
Starship的绝热瓦应该更加耐久 是与机身栓接在一起的 而不是粘上的
they're supposedly much more durable and actually bolted to the airframe instead of glued.
我们已经见过太空叉在Starhopper上测试了隔热罩的栓接与材料选择
We've already seen SpaceX test heat shield mounting and material options on Starhopper,
把它们放在极端环境 震动 温度下
putting them through extreme environments, vibrations and temperatures.
太空叉还在货运龙飞船的外面放了几块小型Starship隔热罩材料
They've also experienced reentry when SpaceX put a few small pieces of Starship heat shield
观察其在再入时的表现
on a Dragon Capsule to observe through reentry.
TUFROC, Toughened uni-piece fibrous reinforced oxidization-resistant composite
强化单层纤维增强抗氧化复合材料
不锈钢机身外壳栓接TUFROC的某种改型
Steel body panels and some variant of a TUFROC heat shield bolted to the airframe
应该会比航天飞机更加灵活
should be more resilient than the Space Shuttle,
不锈钢允许形变
considering steel can dent and ding
不会像增强碳纤维那样破碎 更不会像绝热瓦那样噼啪往下掉
and won't completely shatter like reinforced carbon-carbon or simply fall off like the silica tiles.
同时 像死里逃生的STS-27任务一样
But also, just like STS-27's lucky brush with death,
不锈钢的熔点比铝高
steel has a much higher melting point than aluminum.
这使得不锈钢的Starship有着比铝制机身的航天飞机更高的耐热性
This allows for much greater tolerances to heat than the aluminum airframe of the shuttle as we've talked about.
事实上
As a matter of fact,
Starship甚至可以在没有任何附加热防护的情况下完好撑过再入
it's likely Starship could actually almost survive completely intact
with little to no additional heat shielding
因为其他不锈钢部件在再入后几乎都是完好无损的
as other stainless steel components have survived reentry pretty much completely intact.
我已经做好了一起视频 里面甚至讲到了让它排放燃料
Now I've already done a video about, because it even talked about having it bleed fuel,
进行某种发汗冷却
to do a form of transpirational cooling,
但之后这事要么是搁置了 要么可能用在某些温度较高点上了
but that since either fallen off the table or might be utilized in some hotspots.
强度/密度比值 数值越大越好
灰色为20摄氏度 蓝色为-200摄氏度
从左到右分别是 301不锈钢 碳纤维复材 2219铝合金
这也是为什么太空叉从最开始的碳纤维改成了现在的不锈钢
This is one of the biggest reasons SpaceX switched to stainless steel over carbon fiber
因为当你考虑到需要用多少隔热罩时
because by the time you factor in how big of a heat shield is necessary,
不锈钢的优势就体现出来了
stainless steel starts to come ahead
因为它能在失效前耐受更高的温度
as it can handle much higher temperatures in general before it begins to fail.
所以 希望不锈钢机身
Okay, so hopefully a stainless steel body
加上更灵活的栓接热防护系统
and a more resilient bolted on thermal protection system
外加Starship是放在火箭顶端的特点
along with putting Starship on the top of the rocket stack
能够让其避免重蹈哥伦比亚号空难的覆辙
should all help mitigate the risk of a reentry disaster, like Columbia.
那它下面的火箭又如何呢？
So now what about putting this all on top of a rocket booster
火箭下面可是装了至少37台世界最先进最复杂的发动机
that will have at least 37 of the world's most advanced and complicated engines,
也就是全流量分级燃烧循环的猛禽发动机
that is of course the full flow staged combustion cycle Raptor engine.
相比于没有任何运动部件的两枚固推 这怎么能让火箭更安全 故障更少呢？
How could this possibly be safer and have less failures
than a simple pair of solid rocket boosters that have virtually no moving parts?
这就是太空叉更加擅长 更加有经验的地方了
Now here's where SpaceX has some good knowledge and experience.
他们的猎鹰九号火箭在火箭家族里可不太一样
Their Falcon 9 does something fairly unusual in the rocket world,
它的一级使用了九台小发动机 而不是一两个大发动机
which is having nine smaller engines on the booster instead of one or two larger ones.
这让它允许多个发动机失效
This actually allows multiple engine out capability.
基于哪台发动机 在发射何时发生故障
Now depending on which engines fail and at what point in the flight they do fail,
相比于其他火箭 猎鹰九号的九台发动机为自身提供了大量额外的安全裕度
nine engines gives the Falcon 9 a lot of extra safety margin compared to other rockets.
在环形网状结构中 每个发动机都相互隔离放在防爆仓内
Each engine is isolated within a blast containment cell as part of the Octoweb configuration.
这样 即使某一台发动机失效 也不会影响到其他发动机
This is why they can have an engine fail and have it not affect other engines.
再加上现代传感器和计算机的快速反应
Now you mix this in with modern sensors and quick acting computers,
火箭应该会在发动机发生严重故障之前就把它关闭
and the rocket should be able to shut an engine down before that engine has a catastrophic failure.
太空叉的梅林发动机已经相当可靠了
SpaceX has developed their Merlin engine to the point of extreme reliability.
实际上 迄今为止 上天的800多台梅林发动机只有一台在飞行中出问题
In fact, only one Merlin has ever shut down in flight out of over 800 merlins being flown to date.
更不用说那次还是很早以前
Not to mention that was very early on in the program,
猎鹰九号遥四火箭执行CRS-1任务
the fourth flight of a Falcon 9 for mission CRS-1 to be exact.
从那之后 梅林发动机的可靠性是100%
And since then the engine has been 100% reliable.
所以总的算下来 梅林发动机至今可靠性为99.88%
So in total, the Merlin engine to date has proven to be 99.88% reliable,
再加上一级的冗余度
mix that with redundancy on the first stage,
你会得到一枚无比可靠的一级火箭
and you wind up with an incredibly reliable booster.
更不用说猎鹰九号一级上的某些梅林发动机
Not to mention the fact that some of the Merlins on the first stage of the Falcon 9
每次发射还要额外点火两三次来进行着陆
have to fire up and extra two or three times per flight in order to land.
接下来说点好玩的 给你们看看历史上其他火箭发动机
But just for funsies, let's actually take a look at some other rocket engines throughout history
看看他们可靠性如何
and see how reliable they have been.
不过提前说好
But just a little caveat,
可靠性这东西不好说 因为相关因素太多了
it gets really difficult to just say reliability, because there's so many other factors,
比如发动机重新点火 比如缺点火剂之类的
especially when you factor in relighting of engines, or running out of TEA-TEB ignition fluid or something.
不过这些数字还是能给我们一个 液体火箭发动机可靠性的大致概念
But still, looking at these numbers should give us a decent perspective on
how reliable liquid fueled rocket engines can actually be.
发动机的可靠性
截至2019年12月15日
回过头来 太空叉的梅林发动机目前在发射中可靠性为99.88%
So again, SpaceX's Merlin engine is currently at 99.88% reliability in flight,
比航天飞机主发动机RS-25的可靠性略高
which makes it slightly more reliable than the RS-25 Space Shuttle main engine
后者也在飞行中关机过一次
which also only shut down once in flight,
航天飞机135次任务 每次三台发动机 最终算下来可靠性是99.75%
but with only three engines on 135 missions, it wound up with 99.75% reliability in flight.
接下来是RD-180
Then there's the RD-180,
在86次飞行中有一次提前四秒关机
which technically shut down four seconds early on one of its 86 flights to date,
可靠性98.83%
making it 98.83% reliable,
但你说它可靠性100%也没毛病
although it's also kind of 100% reliable
因为那次任务中
since that particular mission,
OA-6飞船仍然入轨并且任务成功了 有惊无险
OA-6 was able to continue on as and still be a success, but just barely.
所以看大家怎么定义可靠性了 我这里把98.83%和100%都写上
So we can say between 98.83% and 100% depending on how you define engine reliability.
发动机提前关闭是一种故障
I mean, shutting down before intended is considered a failure of the engine,
如果那次再提前一秒关机 任务就失败了
had that happened at any point before that, the mission would have failed.
但对于Atlas V火箭来说 任务还是成功的
But I would consider it a successful mission for the Atlas V
因为半人马上面级救回来了
since the Centaur upper stage could compensate for the failure.
发动机的可靠性
截至2019年12月15日
那毛子的另一个发动机呢？
But how about another Russian engine?
安装在联盟号上的RD-107和兄弟型号RD-108
The RD-107 and its brother the RD-108 that power the Soyuz rocket.
联盟号这个火箭种类繁多 发射次数太多了
Now this rocket has flown so many times and for so long in so many different forms,
跟早期的联盟号火箭相比的话有点不太公平
it's definitely not fair to compare the early days of the Soyuz rocket,
何况那时候的数据也不好找
besides that the data is really hard to find.
发动机的可靠性
截至2019年12月15日
所以我们只统计21世纪使用RD-107和RD-108的267次飞行
So let's look at the 267 flights in the 21st century which use an RD-107 and RD-108,
一共1335台发动机 只有一台发生故障
of the 1,335 engines fired in this century, only one has failed,
可靠性99.92%
giving the RD-107 and RD-108 a 99.92% in flight reliability.
而上过天的最可靠的发动机
But one of the most reliable engines ever flown
实际上是助力土星五号的F-1发动机
was actually the monster F-1 engine that powered the Saturn V.
土星五号13次飞行
The 13 times the Saturn V flew,
所有65台F-1发动机全部100%成功
all 65 F-1 engines that powered those flights were 100% successful.
有没有人想在评论弹幕里问阿波罗13号中央的F-1发动机不是失效了吗
Now before you hop in the comments section and say but didn't Apollo 13 have a center F-1 fail?
错 失效的是二级的J-2发动机
No, that was a J-2 on the second stage.
在F-1的可靠性上貌似有一股曼德拉效应
There seems to be a Mandela effect on F-1 reliability where everyone,
包括我自己也总记成F-1在发射的时候出过故障
including myself, tends to think an F-1 failed on ascent.
那么我们就假设 既然Starship上有很多猛禽发动机 将来就会有大量的数据
So let's assume since there'll be a ton of data on the Raptor engines since the Starship has so many of them,
并且随着Starship几次飞行之后
and they fly Starship a few times over and over,
太空叉最终会让它的可靠性和梅林发动机多发失效的冗余度看齐
that SpaceX will eventually match the reliability of the Merlin engine with multi-engine out capability,
Starship的一级将会非常可靠
the booster should be a very reliable first stage.
我们也假设 太空叉会像猎鹰九号那样保证发动机失效时不会影响其他发动机
Assuming SpaceX does their due diligence to prevent an engine failure
from affecting other engines nearby like they have with the Falcon 9,
还会保证不犯N-1的错误
and, like how the N-1 didn't do a very good job of that.
那么多发并联的确可以让火箭有极高的鲁棒性和可靠性
Having dozens of engines can make for an incredibly robust and reliable vehicle.
好 既然发射时采用多发并联可以让一级火箭安全可靠
Okay sure, having dozens of engines on ascent could help make the booster safe and reliable.
可还有一个更大的问题摆在面前
But what about the big elephant in the room?
为了让Starship能安全载人返回
In order for humans to survive a ride on Starship,
Starship自己不但要进行一个非常酷炫的着陆机动
the Starship itself has to not only perform a pretty wacky landing maneuver,
还要依靠底部三台猛禽发动机中的两台进行反推着陆
but it also relies on two out of three raptor engines working for the landing burn itself.
这安全吗？
Is that actually safe?
人类能相信反推着陆的可靠性吗？
Can we actually rely on propulsive landing for human lives?
我们再次回到猎鹰九号
Well, let's go ahead and take a look at the Falcon 9 again,
毕竟它是历史上去过太空又是反推着陆的唯二的火箭之一
as it's one of only two vehicles in history to perform propulsive landings after reaching space,
不过猎鹰九号和Starship不同的是它不会达到轨道速度
but remember, it isn't reaching orbital velocity either, like Starship is,
所以我们只谈它着陆点火
so we're we're only going to be looking at the landing aspect of it, just the landing burns,
使用发动机进行反推着陆的部分
and using engines as propulsive landings for now.
因为Starship反推着陆的最后阶段
Because the very end of Starship's proposed landing burn
和猎鹰九号功能上和外观上完全一样
will look and function almost exactly like the Falcon 9's.
至今 太空叉回收尝试54次 成功46次
To date, SpaceX has landed 46 out of 54 landing attempts.
这个数字听上去不咋地 可你别忘了
That doesn't sound great, but remember,
在他们第一次着陆前 大家都说这是天方夜谭
before the first landing, it was literally considered impossible.
他们第一次成功的时候感觉简直牛逼疯了
No way, when it happened it was a really big deal.
如果我们只看2017年之后的回收尝试
If we look at just landing attempts starting in 2017
因为在之前他们还在摸索阶段 并且也算攻关成功
after it became a little less experimental and they had it figured out,
我们能够得到非常惊人的数据
we get some pretty surprising numbers.
2017年之后 他们进行了45次回收尝试 只有三次着陆失败
There's been 45 attempts since 2017 and only three of those were failed landings.
三次中没有任何一次是因为梅林发动机自身的故障
None of these three landing failures was due to a failure of a Merlin engine itself,
当然具体来讲还是很复杂的
although again that gets complicated.
按顺序来 2018年2月6日 太空叉的重型猎鹰首飞
Going in order, on February 6th, 2018, SpaceX launched the first Falcon Heavy on its demo mission
除了芯级以外 两枚助推回收成功
and landed all but the center core of the Falcon Heavy.
TEA- TEB: 三乙基铝-三乙基硼
芯级用光了给发动机点火的TEA-TEB
The center core ran out of TEA-TEB
which is the pyrophoric starting fluid that actually ignites the engines.
听起来解决办法很简单
It sounds like there was a pretty easy fix
都不用多加TEA-TEB
and it wasn't actually that they would need more TEA-TEB,
而是调整一下获取TEA-TEB的罐子以及解决问题的时间即可
but just needed to switch which bottle it pulled the TEA-TEB from
and at what point to solve the problem.
之后那年年底 2018年12月5日 CRS-16任务
Then later that year, on December 5th, 2018, for the CRS-16 mission,
全新的Block 5构型猎鹰九号一级着陆失败
a brand new Block 5 Falcon 9 core failed to land
原因是控制格栅舵的液压系统发生卡阻
when the hydraulic system that controls the grid fins seized up.
加个放气阀就能轻松解决
The solution was simply a bleed valve that would prevent it from happening again.
只要梅林发动机没事
As far as the merlin engine goes,
它还是能进行控制 让火箭缓缓落水
it performed perfectly fine and allowed the vehicle to touch down so soft
箭体都是完整的 还能直接拖回港口
that it didn't break apart and could be towed back into port.
最后是上一次重型猎鹰的发射 2019年6月25日 STP-2任务
Lastly the latest Falcon Heavy launch on June 25th, 2019 for the STP-2 mission
芯级着陆尝试又失败了
had a failed center core landing attempt as well.
但太空叉压根没指望它能活过再入 因为速度太快了
SpaceX didn't expect the core to survive reentry due to extremely high velocities
已经达到箭体能承受的极限了
and pushing the vehicle to the absolute limits.
据我们所了解到的 发动机仍然点火 运转良好
So far as we know, the engines themselves still lit up and performed fine
但推力矢量控制系统在再入高温的摧残下被玩坏了
but the thrust vector control that steers them was destroyed due to that spicy reentry heat,
导致着陆时火箭没有足够精确的控制
which made the vehicle lack precise control for landing.
所以发动机没问题 但推力矢量控制出问题了
So the engines themselves were fine but the TVC kinda got destroyed,
所以……很难评价
so it's hard to say.
既然这次是因为芯级火箭已经超出可承受的限制了
Since this was at the outer limits of what the booster is capable of doing,
那真想着陆的时候别这么莽就可以解决了
the solution is just don't push it that hard if you need to land.
如果这是Starship的载人任务
So if this were a Starship mission with people on board,
他们肯定会留足了安全余量
they would've made sure there were healthy margins
保证Starship在安全可操控范围内飞行
that are safely within the operational range of Starship
更不能接受或者设计一个让Starship逼近设计极限的任务
and not even accept a mission or design a mission where they push it to the limits in the first place.
所以人类会相信反推着陆吗？
So can we ever rely on propulsive landings for humans?
以后肯定会的
Eventually, sure.
你想想 阿波罗任务不就是在月球上反推着陆的
Think about it, the Apollo missions relied on purportedly landing on the moon,
人家不是好好的
and that worked out pretty well.
就常规使用来讲 只要留足冗余就行了
As far as everyday usage, as long as there are redundancies in place.
三发点火 允许一发失效就是个不错的开始
Having three engines light and having engine out capability is a good place to start.
那Starship上的其他系统呢？
But what about other systems in place on Starship?
两边巨大的 来回扑棱的机翼怎么说？
What about those giant wingy, flappy, fins things?
要是液压系统发生故障 导致翼面卡阻 重蹈CRS-16覆辙了怎么办？
What if the hydraulic system fails on those and they get stuck,
like what happened on CRS-16?
这个问题只要想想民航客机和航天飞机就行了
Well for this, we need to look no further than airliners and the Space Shuttle.
这就是冗余发挥作用的地方
Here's where good old redundancy comes into play.
民航客机在液压系统故障时会失控 会无法放下起落架
Airliners would lose control and be unable to operate their landing gear as intended
if the hydraulic systems failed.
航天飞机也同样
Same goes for the Space Shuttle.
正因如此 才会有备份发电机 备份的泵 备份的管线
Which is exactly why there are redundant generators, redundant pumps, redundant lines,
几乎所有系统都有冗余备份
basically everything in that system up is redundant.
拿CRS-16的液压故障来说事其实很不公平
It's actually not very wise to compare the CRS-16 failed hydraulic system and say,
"哎呀呀这要是放在Starship上那不完犊子了"
see, what if that happens on Starship?
因为猎鹰九号的一级着陆对任务本身没有影响
Because a Falcon 9 booster landing isn't mission critical,
对人的安全更没影响
let alone required for human safety,
所以他们为了系统的简化 就故意没加冗余
so they have intentionally lacked redundancy for simplicity.
但有一样东西 没法冗余 而且一出事就是大事
But there is one big thing that isn't redundant and can be catastrophic if it fails,
后果很严重的那种
and boy do I mean big,
那就是燃料罐
because that's the fuel tank slash the fuselage.
讲道理 这才是我最关心的问题
This is honestly my biggest area of concern.
而且说实话 这正是太空叉一次又一次翻车的地方
And to be quite frank, it's the one thing SpaceX has had bad luck with over and over and over.
猎鹰九号的第一次失败是由于一个装氦的碳纤维缠绕压力容器(COPV)
The first failure of a Falcon 9 was due to
a helium filled composite over-wrapped pressure vessel or COPV,
它们是用来给燃料和液氧罐加压的
these pressurize the fuel and oxygen tanks,
2015年6月28日 CRS-7任务中发生破损 摧毁了上面级的液氧罐
and one broke loose in the upper stage oxygen tank on June 28th, 2015 for the CRS-7 mission.
导致火箭迅速解体 船箭俱毁
This caused a rapid unscheduled disassembly and complete loss of the rocket and it's payload.
版权原因 视频中画面仅为爆炸后结果
想看完整画面 搜索AMOS-6即可
第二次就是2016年9月1日臭名昭著的AMOS-6
The next failure was the infamous AMOS-6 anomaly on September 1st, 2016.
上面级的氦气罐再一次出问题导致压力过高
Again, an over pressurization due to a failed helium tank in the upper stage
让加满燃料准备在发射台上进行静态点火测试的火箭原地爆炸
caused a complete and total loss of the vehicle
as it was being fueled up on the launch pad for a static fire test.
同样这里不放出非法泄露的爆炸视频
然后是2019年4月20日载人龙飞船
Then we have the Crew Dragon anomaly on April 20th, 2019.
当时太空叉打算在地面测试逃逸系统
This is when SpaceX was testing the launch abort system on the ground
一块结冰的四氧化二氮射穿了钛合金阀门
and had a frozen chunk of nitrogen tetroxide shoot through a titanium valve
导致系统发生破裂 飞船原地爆炸
causing a rupture in the system and total loss of the vehicle.
离现在最近的 并且最吓人的
And most recently and perhaps most alarmingly,
就是2019年11月20日Starship MK-1原型机的事故
we actually saw a failure of a Starship MK-1 prototype on November 20th, 2019
在压力测试中直接把顶盖崩飞
when we watched it blow its top off from over-pressurization during a pressure test.
但是！我要澄清一点
BUT, now this I'll give a bit of a pass to.
这枚火箭和进行的测试和未来实际工况相差甚远
This vehicle and that test was nowhere near future operating conditions.
太空叉想对该原型机进行远超设计极限的压力测试
SpaceX was pushing this prototype much further than normal operating ranges
原型机也是非常早期非常粗制滥造的版本
and these were the shotty welds of the very initial rough prototype
它不能代表未来 改良后的成品火箭
and they don't represent a future, the more refined vehicle like it will be.
但一想起未来装满燃料没有逃逸系统的载人Starship 难免感觉有点慌
But it sure does get a bit spooky when you think that if that was a fully fueled Starship,
and there were people on board there would have been no aborting from it.
Starship逃逸系统可选方案
估计接下来有人会问 Starship可以有哪些逃逸方案？
So I guess this leads us to the question of what options does Starship have to abort?
我们已经讲过它在设计上为避免遇到航天飞机相同设计缺陷的考虑因素
We've already gone over what design considerations
make it avoid the same design flaws as the Space Shuttle,
可它还是没有实打实的逃逸系统
but it still is lacking an actual abort system.
那它能进行逃逸吗？
So can it abort at all?
我们先讲清逃逸的种类
Well, let's first make sure we're clear on the types of abort options.
发射台逃逸 发射中逃逸 逃逸入轨 终止任务 之间是有很多区别的
There's a big difference between a pad abort, an inflight abort,
aborting to orbit and aborting a mission in general.
发射台逃逸是火箭还在发射台上的时候把飞船带离火箭
A pad abort is the option to pull the spacecraft free from the rocket while still on the pad.
这个时间段还是很危险的 因为火箭加满了高压易爆的燃料
This is actually a pretty dangerous time while the vehicle is fully fueled,
full of highly pressurized explosive material.
那么Starship能进行发射台逃逸吗？
So can Starship do a pad abort?
能 也不能
Yes-ish and no.
如果故障出在Starship上面级自身 比如燃料罐损毁之类的
If the problem is in the Starship upper stage itself, like a tank rupturing or something,
那显然答案就是不能
the simple answer is no.
但如果故障出在一级火箭？
But what if the problem is with the booster?
如果一级火箭突然爆炸
If the booster suddenly ruptures,
Starship的上面级可以紧急执行猛禽发动机的快速点火
the upper stage of Starship could perform an emergency quick start of the Raptor engines
可以避免Starship飞船跌落进一级火箭爆炸后的火海当中
which could help prevent the Starship from just falling down onto
a pile of what was once a Super Heavy booster and is now a flaming hellish landscape.
如果将包括真空版本发动机在内的所有发动机一起点火
If all engines are fired, including its vacuum optimized engines,
Starship可以有刚好足够的推重比
Starship would have just barely enough thrust
慢慢离开发射台 转移到安全的着陆区域
to slowly get away from the pad and divert to a safe landing area.
这个前提是损毁的一级并没有严重伤及Starship的飞行能力
That is assuming a failed Super Heavy booster didn't damage the Starship bad enough to make it un-flyable.
毕竟你不是要跑出压力波的范围
Don't forget, you're not trying to outrun the pressure wave,
除非你能瞬间让周围声速降到零
because spoiler alert, unless you can go zero to the speed of sound literally instantly, you can't outrun it.
所以如果你人在火箭里面
So if you're inside a pressure vessel,
你至少得先活过初始那波爆炸
you should at least survive the initial blast.
大家可能还会问 真空发动机能在海平面点火吗？
You also might ask how could they fire vacuum optimized engines at sea level,
大气性质相差太多 很难点火才对啊
That was a big part of the air spec you can't really do that.
呃 根据老马所说
Well according to Elon,
他们有双钟形喷管的设计
they could have dual bell nozzle design
并且让喷管固定在飞船底部从而保持稳定
and fix the nozzle to the hull wall which can stabilize it.
总之 点得着
And in general, yes,
你可以在紧急情况下在海平面给真空发动机喷管点火
you can actually fire a standard vacuum nozzle at sea level in an emergency,
但很有可能会失败 可如果其他方法都不能用 这个方法总该试试
but it's very likely to fail but why not try if the other option is complete failure anyway?
所以 发射台逃逸 可能 或许大概……
So pad abort, kinda, maybe a little,
反正至少比航天飞机在发射台上完全没法逃逸的强多了
well it's at least better than the Space Shuttle's full lack of abort options while sitting on the pad.
发射中逃逸亦同理
The same goes for an inflight abort.
发射中逃逸 顾名思义 就是火箭在飞的时候进行逃逸
An in-flight abort is just what it sounds like, aborting while the rocket is flying.
同样假设上面级没炸
Again, assuming the upper stage isn't the culprit of the problem,
Starship理论上有能力将自身带离火箭
the Starship could theoretically pull away
并执行所需机动 然后再入 找个地方着陆
and perform whatever maneuver necessary to re-enter and land somewhere else
或者最坏的情况 也可以进行海上紧急软着陆
or worst case scenario do a soft splashdown emergency landing.
同样比航天飞机有更多的选择 更多的机会
Again, it should have more options and opportunities than the Space Shuttle did.
当Starship和一级分离后
Once Starship has detached from Super Heavy,
如果燃料不足以入轨 那除了执行再入流程以外也没别的选择了
there really aren't any abort options other than aborting to a safe reentry profile
and then reentering if it can't achieve orbit.
不过幸运的是 Starship的操控面
But luckily, with the control surfaces on Starship,
可以让它有更充分的气动性能
they could greatly alter their aerodynamic profile and the dynamics
从而进行安全可控的再入
for a handful of safe reentry options.
相比于不能改变形状的返回舱 这样的优势就很大
This is helpful compared to say a capsule which can't change its shape
实际上 返回舱的形状面积还会让工程师们在发射流程上加入额外考虑
and actually has areas in a launch profile that the engineers need to avoid.
目前来讲 如果用标准的单发RL-10半人马上面级发射波音的星际线飞船
For instance, if a standard single engine RL-10 Centaur upper stage was used on Boeing's Starliner,
发射流程中会有很大一部分时间段
there would be large portions of the profile
在逃逸再入的时候可能会有致命的巨大过载
where an abort would be deadly due to extreme reentry forces.
因此 波音和ULA决定使用双发动机版本的半人马上面级
Boeing and ULA therefore had to opt with a two engine variant of the Centaur upper stage
发射流程更加安全 整个发射过程中的逃逸窗口也更加安全
that could fly a safer profile which allows for a safe abort window throughout the entire ascent.
当然 再入的时候也没有其他逃逸的选择了
And of course, on reentry there really isn't ever an abort option.
再入必须成功
Reentry just needs to work.
即使有那么种再入中使用的逃逸选项
Even if there was a mechanical abort option during reentry,
估计也没啥大用
it likely wouldn't be very helpful.
当然 虽说被动稳定的返回舱加上简单的防热大底
Now of course a passively stable capsule with a simple ablative heat shield
出错的概率极低
has very little that could go wrong,
但控制翼面的冗余液压系统
but again, redundant hydraulics for control surfaces
和能承受高温的结构
and a structure that can handle high temperatures in general
也应该能为Starship的再入提供不错的缓冲
should offer a decent buffer in reentry for Starship.
逃逸系统是否真的会让火箭更安全
终于到了本期视频的干货了！
Okay, we're finally getting to the true meat of the question.
火箭上安装逃逸系统 会更安全吗？
Is it actually better to have an abort system on a rocket, period?
想要回答这个问题 我们快速回顾一下所有逃逸事件和人类航天的事故
To do that, let's quickly go over all the aborts and all the accidents of human spaceflight
看看逃逸系统到底有没有用
and determine whether or not an abort system could've helped.
纵观整个人类入轨级的航天飞行史
Looking at the history of orbital spaceflight
只有18人在航天飞行活动中死亡
there's only been 18 deaths actually occurring during orbital spaceflight activities.
第一起是1967年非常早期的联盟号任务 降落伞故障
The first death being a parachute failure on the very first Soyuz mission in 1967
宇航员弗拉迪米尔·科马洛夫遇难
which killed cosmonaut Vladimir Komarov.
逃逸系统在这起事故中无用
An abort system would not have helped.
下一起悲剧是1971年发射的联盟11号
The next tragedy was Soyuz 11 in 1971
飞船失压 三名宇航员遇难
which decompression of the spacecraft actually led to the deaths of three cosmonauts.
这是迄今为止唯一一起人类在卡门线外的死亡事故
To this day, this is the only incident in which humans died in space above the Karman line.
逃逸系统在这起事故中无用
An abort system would not have helped.
下一起是刚提到过的1986年挑战者号空难
Next we have the Space Shuttle Challenger disaster in 1986 which we've already talked about.
如果有逃逸机构的话 或许会挽救那七名乘员的生命
A mechanical abort system would have likely saved the crew of seven.
最后是2003年哥伦比亚号空难
Lastly we have the Space Shuttle Columbia disaster in 2003
又一次是七名宇航员全部遇难
which again, tragically killed the crew of seven.
逃逸系统在这起事故中应该不会有用
An abort system would likely not have helped.
如果有自带防热罩的逃生舱或许还有机会
There's a chance if an escape pod had its own heat shield and the like, it may have helped,
但在再入的时候逃逸本身就不是啥好主意
but it's unlikely aborting during reentry would be a very good option.
接下来我们看看 逃逸系统启动的案例
Now let's look at the number of times a crewed orbital launch escape system has aborted.
数量非常少
This number is very small.
迄今为止 逃逸系统只启动过三次
Today, an abort system actually armed for a flight has only been triggered three times.
第一次逃逸系统的启动实际上是在联盟号的一次无人试飞任务中
The first time an abort system was used was actually on an un-crewed test flight of Soyuz
1966年 联盟号7K-OK飞船
for the Soyuz 7K-OK number one mission in 1966.
一枚助推器点火失败 发射重置
The launch was reset when a strap-on booster failed to ignite.
地面小组前去查看火箭情况
The ground crew went out to inspect the rocket
结果在发射取消后27分钟 逃逸塔突然启动
when suddenly, 27 minutes after the scrub the launch tower activated
因为由于地球自转 箭载陀螺仪检测到8度的偏差
because its gyroscope noticed it was 8 degrees off axis
from where it thought it should be due to the Earth's rotation.
逃逸系统的尾焰使火箭第三级起火
The firing of the abort system ended up lighting the third stage on fire,
之后导致火箭整体在发射台爆炸 一名地面小组成员遇难
and then the rest of the rocket blew up on the pad killing one ground crew personnel.
在这起案例中 逃逸系统引发了事故 并导致一人死亡
In this case an abort system caused a failure and a death.
逃逸系统的第二次启动
The next time an abort system was fired,
是唯一一次载人的发射台逃逸
was the only time there's been a pad abort with crew on board.
1983年9月26日
On September 26th, 1983,
联盟T-10-1号飞船从在发射台起火的火箭上逃逸
when the crew of Soyuz T-10-1 had to abort from their Soyuz rocket
that had caught on fire while still on the launch pad.
在安全逃逸并在四公里外着陆后
After safely aborting and landing four kilometers downrange,
救援队见到他们时发现他们受了轻伤且吓得不轻
the crew was bruised up and shaken when they were met by the recovery crew.
赶紧让他们抽两口烟喝口伏特加压压惊
They were given cigarettes and shots of vodka to relax.
这个案例中 显然逃逸系统救命了
In this case obviously the launch abort system saved lives.
最后一次逃逸系统启动是2018年联盟号MS-10任务
Lastly, the abort system was triggered on another Soyuz mission MS-10 in 2018
助推器分离出现故障
when there was a problem at booster separation
导致助推器破坏了芯级
that caused a booster to rupture the core stage.
触发了逃逸系统
This triggered the abort system,
不是用的逃逸塔 因为它几秒前就抛掉了
not the full tower which had just been jettisoned a few seconds prior,
而是用的整合在飞船整流罩上的小型逃逸系统
but a smaller abort system integrated onto the fairing covering the crew module.
这个例子中 逃逸系统也救命了
In this case, the abort system saved lives,
但如果逃逸系统没有启动 单纯关闭发动机 分离飞船应该也是足够逃生的
but perhaps simply shutting down the engines and detaching from the booster
would have been sufficient without a mechanical escape system active.
任务终止的例子只有两个
There are really only about two other flights which were aborted,
第一次是1975年联盟号7K-T-39任务
the first was Soyuz 7K-T-39 in 1975,
在逃逸塔分离后任务终止
which aborted after the escape tower and fairing were jettisoned,
逃逸系统肯定显然无用 毕竟逃逸塔都扔了
An abort system obviously wouldn't have helped as it had already been ditched.
然后是唯一一次航天飞机的任务终止 1985年STS-51-F任务
Then there's the only Space Shuttle to abort, STS-51-F in 1985.
在一台RS-25发动机关机后 它执行了逃逸入轨机动
It performed an abort to orbit maneuver when one of the RS-25 main engines shut down.
这次逃逸系统还是没帮上忙 因为没必要
Again, an abort system wouldn't have helped as it was unnecessary.
载人航天逃逸系统成功率(1961-2019)
绿色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统启用)  红色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统无用)    黑色 有人员死亡(由逃逸系统引发)
黄色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统未使用)     蓝色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统或许有用)
所以总的来看 迄今为止
So in the grand scheme of things, to date,
逃逸系统只救过两次命
a mechanical abort system has only saved lives twice,
它或许能阻止一次悲剧 但它又导致了一次悲剧
it may have prevented one tragedy and in one case it actually created a tragedy.
所以在人类迄今为止320次航天飞行当中
So out of the 320 orbital human human flights to date,
只有三次任务是实打实地需要使用逃逸系统
only three missions in total necessitated the use of an abort system,
占载人航天发射的1%
or less than 1% of crewed launches.
还有三次发射 逃逸系统根本无用
There were another three launches where an abort system wouldn't have helped at all,
还有两次任务终止 没有用上任何逃逸系统
and two that aborted without any kind of escape system.
如果我们只看最近30年的 从90年代开始
And if we look at the last 30 years of human spaceflight, from the 90's on,
载人航天逃逸系统成功率(1963-2019)
绿色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统启用)  红色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统无用)    黑色 有人员死亡(由逃逸系统引发)
黄色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统未使用)     蓝色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统或许有用)
载人航天逃逸系统成功率(1965-2019)
绿色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统启用)  红色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统无用)    黑色 有人员死亡(由逃逸系统引发)
黄色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统未使用)     蓝色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统或许有用)
载人航天逃逸系统成功率(1966-2019)
绿色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统启用)  红色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统无用)    黑色 有人员死亡(由逃逸系统引发)
黄色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统未使用)     蓝色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统或许有用)
载人航天逃逸系统成功率(1968-2019)
绿色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统启用)  红色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统无用)    黑色 有人员死亡(由逃逸系统引发)
黄色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统未使用)     蓝色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统或许有用)
载人航天逃逸系统成功率(1970-2019)
绿色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统启用)  红色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统无用)    黑色 有人员死亡(由逃逸系统引发)
黄色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统未使用)     蓝色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统或许有用)
载人航天逃逸系统成功率(1972-2019)
绿色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统启用)  红色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统无用)    黑色 有人员死亡(由逃逸系统引发)
黄色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统未使用)     蓝色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统或许有用)
载人航天逃逸系统成功率(1974-2019)
绿色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统启用)  红色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统无用)    黑色 有人员死亡(由逃逸系统引发)
黄色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统未使用)     蓝色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统或许有用)
载人航天逃逸系统成功率(1976-2019)
绿色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统启用)  红色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统无用)    黑色 有人员死亡(由逃逸系统引发)
黄色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统未使用)     蓝色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统或许有用)
载人航天逃逸系统成功率(1977-2019)
绿色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统启用)  红色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统无用)    黑色 有人员死亡(由逃逸系统引发)
黄色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统未使用)     蓝色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统或许有用)
载人航天逃逸系统成功率(1979-2019)
绿色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统启用)  红色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统无用)    黑色 有人员死亡(由逃逸系统引发)
黄色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统未使用)     蓝色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统或许有用)
载人航天逃逸系统成功率(1981-2019)
绿色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统启用)  红色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统无用)    黑色 有人员死亡(由逃逸系统引发)
黄色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统未使用)     蓝色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统或许有用)
载人航天逃逸系统成功率(1983-2019)
绿色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统启用)  红色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统无用)    黑色 有人员死亡(由逃逸系统引发)
黄色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统未使用)     蓝色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统或许有用)
载人航天逃逸系统成功率(1985-2019)
绿色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统启用)  红色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统无用)    黑色 有人员死亡(由逃逸系统引发)
黄色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统未使用)     蓝色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统或许有用)
载人航天逃逸系统成功率(1988-2019)
绿色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统启用)  红色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统无用)    黑色 有人员死亡(由逃逸系统引发)
黄色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统未使用)     蓝色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统或许有用)
载人航天逃逸系统成功率(1990-2019)
绿色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统启用)  红色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统无用)    黑色 有人员死亡(由逃逸系统引发)
黄色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统未使用)     蓝色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统或许有用)
180次飞行中只有一次用上了逃逸系统
only one launch out of 180-ish launches required a launch abort system actually be used,
所以只有大约0.5%的飞行 会让逃逸系统带来一点点好处
so only about half a percent of flights would see any benefit from a launch escape system at all.
如何提升无逃逸系统火箭的安全性
在回答"逃逸系统是必需的吗"之前
Now before we answer the question are abort systems necessary,
我们先谈谈另一件事情
let's just take a look at one more thing.
我们如何提升火箭整体的安全性到不需要逃逸系统的地步？
How can we improve the safety of rockets over all
so we don't need an abort system period?
我认为这个问题的答案是 我们要多射几发 多射很多很多发
I think the answer to this question is we need to fly more a lot more, a lot more.
我们要反复使用我们的系统很多次才能找到缺陷在哪
And we need to reuse systems over and over so we can see where things are weakest
才能让安全性有所突破
and where we can make the greatest improvements in safety.
我们来看一下飞机的安全性
Let's look at airliner safety.
飞行里程/事故(百万公里)
这张图是商业航空旅行 平均每飞行多少公里才会出一次事故
This is a chart showing how many kilometers of commercial airline travel happen per accident over time.
不幸的是数据只有1929年之后的
Unfortunately this data only goes back to 1929
再早期航空旅行更为所欲为的年代数据都没有显示
and doesn't even show the very early, wild, wild west days of air travel.
但在不到一个世纪的时间里
But in less than a century,
航空业的安全性提升了三个数量级
the industry's safety record improved by three orders of magnitude.
我真的希望能看看人类航空界最开始三十年的安全数据
Now I really really wish we had data on the first three decades of human air flight,
但很可惜 找不到那些数据
but unfortunately the data is not available,
但应该趋势上不会离这个表格差太多
but I wouldn't be too surprised if it didn't look too far off from this chart.
接下来是每年入轨级发射的成功率
Now this is actually the orbital launch success rate per year.
成功率(%) 蓝色 入轨级火箭成功率(无人与载人 1957-2017) 绿色 航空成功率 (只考虑商业航班)
注意到人类很快就把成功率提升到了90%以上
Notice how quickly humans got into the upper 90 percentile.
但之后就停滞不前了
But then it stalled.
我们把航空业同样时间的数据也画在表格上
Let's compare that to the airline industry during the same time frame.
没错 当时人类航空技术已经很厉害了
Yeah, humans had pretty much nailed down how to fly by then,
所以只有你把表格放大上万倍 才能看到飞行成功率的进步
so it isn't until you zoom into the tens of thousands
that you can actually even begin to decipher an improvement on flight success rate
毕竟之后就是在追求概率里有几个9了
because we're well into chasing the nine's in reliability at this point.
我认为这当中有几条原因
And I think there's a few reasons for this.
首先 人类入轨级的发射还不到6000次
First off, in total there hasn't even been 6,000 orbital launches ever.
相比于2018年一年近四千万次的商业航空飞行
Compare that to the almost 40 million commercial air departures in 2018 alone
你会发现航天发射仍然是太少了
and you realize just how rare spaceflight is still.
我敢说前六千次飞机的飞行尝试 成功率肯定和航天的一样惨
I'll bet the first 6,000 flight attempts of airplanes had a similarly awful flight record as well.
6000次飞行可能很快就能完成
6,000 flights was probably just achieved in a much, much quicker timeframe
毕竟造飞机的门槛比造火箭低多了
and with a significantly lower barrier of entry than building a rocket.
或许我们拿火箭和飞机对比不太合适
Now we probably shouldn't be comparing rockets to airplanes,
因为送火箭去太空 再安全带回来是真的相当相当难
because getting a rocket to space and bringing it back safely is really, really hard,
比造飞机难了几个数量级
orders of magnitude harder than flying an airplane to begin with.
你用纸都能折出来飞机
You can make airplanes out of paper,
你要是像Peter Steeple那样牛逼 拿啥都能造出来飞机
or if you are Peter Steeple you can make airplanes out of pretty much anything.
但看到我们能把飞机的可靠性快速提升到这么高 还是很有意思的
But it is fun to see how quickly we can actually really improve reliability,
需要的只是时间罢了
it just takes more and more time.
只要功夫深 它们的可靠性可以提升的非常快
But it is fun to compare how quickly things can become reliable once you do them often enough.
所以我们如何让火箭更加可靠？答案很简单
The answer to what can we do to make rockets more reliable is simple.
多射几发 多回收 多复用 射完别扔
Fly them more often and fly reusable rockets over and over instead of throwing them away.
只有这样 我们才能不断靠近航空业的可靠性
Only then will we begin to get anywhere near airliner like reliability.
逃逸系统对载人航天的必要性
终于到了总结这一切的时候了
So it's time we finally wrap this all up.
发射逃逸系统
Launch abort systems.
它们是必需的吗？
Are they necessary?
它们会让宇航员更安全吗？
Do they actually make astronauts safer?
它还会继续存在吗？
Do we need them going forward?
如果会 我们未来会经常用到它吗？
If so, will we always need them in the future?
载人航天逃逸系统成功率(1961-2019)
绿色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统启用)  红色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统无用)    黑色 有人员死亡(由逃逸系统引发)
黄色 逃逸成功(逃逸系统未使用)     蓝色 有人员死亡(逃逸系统或许有用)
还记得发射逃逸系统一共拯救过多少次乘员的生命吗？
So remember when we looked at how many times a launch abort system would have saved the lives of crew
记得那个数字有多小吗？
and it's a surprisingly small number?
当然 对于现在的火箭 我仍然认为有逃逸系统是好的
Well, I still think it's a good idea for this generation of rockets.
我认为NASA 太空叉和波音都知道猎鹰九号和AtlasV火箭
I think NASA, SpaceX and Boeing are right to assume the Falcon 9 and Atlas V,
尽管很可靠
as reliable of rockets as they are,
但还是缺少有说服力的数据来证明它们足够安全 可以完全不用逃逸系统
still lack significant flight data to really be considered safe enough without a launch abort system.
但别忘了 逃逸系统也会增加系统复杂度 自身也会出问题
But don't forget launch abort system is still bring their own complications and problems with them.
记得太空叉的载人龙飞船逃逸系统测试时的自爆吗？
Remember how SpaceX's Crew Dragon Capsule blew up when testing the abort system?
而且实际上波音的逃逸系统也在发射台上发生过起火事件
And actually Boeing had problems with their launch abort system catching fire on the pad too.
你把更多的零件和一个小型火箭作为了一个额外系统 它同样会出故障
You're basically taking more parts and a small rocket and attaching all these extra systems, that can also fail,
然后你又把这个额外的系统装在了飞船上
and you are putting them directly on your crew module anyway.
诚然 为了让它们更安全我们下了很多功夫
Sure, a lot of work goes into making them safe,
但你解决火箭问题的办法是在上面再加一个小火箭
but you're solving the problems of rockets by sticking more rockets on them.
这就好比在747肚子里放一架塞斯纳螺旋桨飞机
That would be like putting a Cessna prop plane inside of a 747
当747出故障的时候 你可以开塞斯纳逃跑
in case the 747 fails you can fly away on the Cessna.
你与其另买一架塞斯纳 还不如好好保养你的747让它更可靠
You're probably better off just making sure your maintenance is up to speed
rather than going and buying a Cessna.
这就好像总有人会问
It's like how people ask all the time
龙飞船上的Super Draco逃逸发动机可以作为降落伞故障时的备份吗
if the Super Draco Abort motors could be used as a backup to the parachutes if the parachutes fail,
你非这么问 那理论上讲它当然可以啦
and the answer is, technically, yes of course they could.
但你有那功夫测试逃逸系统 流程 让逃逸发动机越来越安全可靠
But by the time you certify that procedure, those systems, and make them safe and reliable,
你为啥不先保证你降落伞不会出故障 让降落伞越来越可靠呢
you probably would've been better off
just making sure your parachutes don't fail in the first place and make them more reliable.
同样 你愿意呕心沥血开发这套逃逸系统 流程 飞行包线 及其子系统
In the same way, would you rather engineer an abort system,
put together all these procedures and envelopes and subsystems
还是专注于让整个火箭更加可靠呢？
or focus on making the entire vehicle that much safer.
总有一天 你可以用更少的零件打造更可靠系统
At some point, you can actually arguably achieve a more reliable system over all if it has fewer parts.
我认为马一龙在2019年Starship更新发布会上表达的想法就很好
I think Elon Musk has a good point when he said this in the 2019 Starship update.
没有部件就是最好的部件
大成若缺 其用不弊
The best part is no part.
没有流程就是最好的流程
大盈若冲 其用不穷
The best process is no process,
没有那个部件 就没有它的重量 就少了它的成本 更不会出新的故障
it weighs nothing, costs nothing, can't go wrong.
这就是所说的 没有部件就是最好的部件
此所谓 大成若缺 其用不弊
So as obvious as that sounds, the best part is no part.
我印象最深的是太空叉设计会议中说的
The thing I'm most impressed with when I have design meetings at SpaceX
"你没有设计什么?"
is what did you un-design?
没有设计就是最好的设计
Undesigning is the best thing.
直接放弃掉 就是最好的选择
Just delete it, that's the best thing.
所以我觉得问题应该是
So I guess the question should be
我会敢坐没有逃逸系统的Starship吗？
would I ride on a Starship without an abort system?
目前来讲 不会
For now, the answer is no.
我觉得起码得看到它无人飞行个几十次吧
I think we should see at least a few dozen flights without crew first,
这样应该能看到它的极限在哪
We should find the limits and boundaries,
或许会失败那么一两次
maybe have some failures or two
等我们看到它能连续飞十多次不出任何故障
and only once we've seen Starships flying 10 plus times reliably without any failures,
我或许会考虑去坐坐
would I consider getting on one.
但我自己又有点胆小
But I'm also kind of a chicken,
我应该不会让它缺斤少两就上天
I don't think I'm cut out for anything less.
但我的确相信将来会有人愿意冒险在计划早期乘坐Starship
I do think it could be possible
we see humans who are willing to risk it on Starship early on in the program,
而如果NASA的宇航员要坐
and if it's NASA astronauts on board,
那他们肯定会强制要求安装逃逸系统
I wouldn't be surprised if they would require an abort system.
尤其太空叉很可能像猎鹰九号那样一边加燃料一边上人
Especially since SpaceX will likely load and go their fuel, just like they do the Falcon 9,
这意味着乘员会在燃料流动的时候登船
meaning the crew will need to be onboard as fuel flows.
总的来讲 燃料流动 加压的时候 比它加满以后停在那更危险
In general, it's more dangerous to be filling and pressurizing a vehicle
than to have it sitting there stable and fully fueled.
所以除非太空叉会为Starship更改加注流程
So unless SpaceX can change that procedure for Starship,
我觉得NASA肯定不会很快同意让他们的宇航员登上一个没有逃逸系统的火箭
I honestly can't really imagine NASA wanting any of their astronauts on board
without an abort system again any time soon.
归根结底 你不可能解决你无法预知的问题
At the end of the day you can't fix the problems you don't know are there.
就像太空叉发现超低温下COPV会出问题时有多震惊一样
Just like how SpaceX was so surprised to discover problems
with cryogenics and composite over-wrapped pressure vessels,
或是结构的失效 钛合金阀门爆炸亦同理
or the failure of a strut, or titanium valve exploding,
有时在那个故障出现之前你就是完全发现不到它
sometimes you simply don't discover a design flaw until it rears its ugly head.
这也是为什么我认为 让火箭多射几次 多射很多很多次 是非常重要的
So that's why I think it's vital we see these things fly, fly often, and fly over and over.
只有这样我们才能有足够多的可靠性记录
Only then will I think there's a proven reliability track record
让我们相信它已经安全到不需要逃逸系统了
that would make it a safe enough option to not have an abort system.
那么大家怎样看？
So what do you think?
逃逸系统 是好还是坏？
Abort systems, are they good or are they bad?
你会去坐没有逃逸系统的火箭吗？
Would you get on a rocket that doesn't have an abort system.
说到底 这才是最终的趋势所在
At the end of the day that's really what it comes down to.
我能看到这个争论的两面性
I can see both sides of this argument.
你可能说 装逃逸系统当然更安全
I can see where you might say obviously it can make things safer
因为如果火箭出故障 你至少有个"备份火箭"
Because if the rocket fails you at least have a backup rocket,
可同时你这又是在增加部件
at the same time you're adding more parts.
所以或许有那么一种见解优雅的设计方案根本不需要那么啰嗦的额外部件
So maybe there's some elegance to the simplicity of the design that doesn't have all these extra parts,
单纯地让它们更加可靠就行了
and just focus on making those more reliable.
这我就说不好了
But I don't know.
欢迎大家在评论区留下你们的想法
Let me know your thoughts in the comments below.
如果你们还有其他问题 也请务必让我知道
And also be sure and let me know if you have any other questions
可以是关于Starship 逃逸系统 不锈钢 猛禽发动机 航天飞机 任何问题都可以
about Starship, abort systems, stainless steel, Raptor engines, Space Shuttles, anything.
任何问题都可以问我 我会尽力在之后的视频中作出解答
Let me know if you have any questions and I'll be sure and try to crank it out on my video list.
我有无数的坑等着填
I have this never ending video list that I just cannot keep up with,
但我肯定会尽力去挨个填满
but I'm really excited to keep cranking away at them.
所以请多多留意 还有好多好玩的内容等着你！
So stay tuned, there's a lot of really good content coming.
和往常一样 万分感谢我所有在Patreon上的赞助者
As always, I owe the biggest thanks in the world to my Patreon supporters,
他们几乎帮我做了一切
who literally helped me do all of this stuff.
为本期视频付出了很多很多
They have been a big, big help on this video,
帮我搜集各种冷知识
trying to find all these fun facts,
帮我一起找那些小知识点
and find little nuggets of information with me,
搜集数据 帮我验证它们
crunching numbers and confirming my stuff is accurate.
所以如果你也想来帮助我
So if you want to help do what I do,
请务必考虑来下方链接成为我的Patreon赞助者
please consider becoming a Patreon supporter by going to Patreon.com/everydayastronaut
你可以进入我们独家的Discord频道 看到独家直播
where you'll gain access to our exclusive Discord, Patreon, and exclusive live streams.
非常感谢！
Thank you.
另外大家上网的时候记得去我的小店看看 地址在下面
And while you're online be sure and check out everydayastronaut.com/shop for limited edition merch.
好多越来越酷炫的东西
Now do notice that the merchandise is getting awesome,
都是手工丝网印刷 手工缝制的
they are all hand screen printed, hand sewn-on patches.
定制的领子标签 贼酷
Custom neck labels, all these really cool things.
而且全都是限量版的
And these awesome designs are limited runs.
看上哪样的话建议赶紧下手
So if you like something you'd better grab it now,
可能过这村就没这店了
because there's a good chance it won't be there next time you click on the website.
你甚至能买到马一龙最喜欢的T恤
And I guess you can even grab what's apparently one of Elon Musk's favorite shirts,
就是全流量分级燃烧循环的那件
the full flow stage combustion cycle shirt.
最近天冷了 我们还有了连帽衫的版本
We also have that as a hoodie version as well just in time for the cool weather.
所以快去瞅瞅吧 能买到好多好东西
So get in there while you can and get some awesome merchandise for yourself.
地址在下面
That's everydayastronaut.com/shop.
感谢大家 感谢观看
Thanks everybody, that's gonna do it for me.
我是《每日宇航员》的Tim Dodd
I'm Tim Dodd, The Everyday Astronaut,
把太空知识带入寻常百姓家
bringing space down to Earth for everyday people.